Inventory of the Herman Recht Papers 1943-1946
Earl Gregg Swem Library, College of William and Mary
- Folders 301-400: 25 September 1944-8 March 1945
  - (4)
    - Folders 351-360: 29 January 1945-3 February 1945 (4, 6)
      Reflects on the time that he and Esther spent together, especially the last part in New York. Sees the movie “Keys of the Kingdom”. Camp is using some of the war prisoners for work, such as coal deliverers and in the mess hall. Hears of the possibility of a coal miners strike if their contract is not extended; talks about Esther buying a fur coat, and his misgivings. Discusses a personal injury case one of his friends in involved with. Sees the movie “Tomorrow, the World.” Has a commander ask to get a vehicle to take his dog to the vet. Talks about the tests required to get a higher rating. Writes about some men in his depart being court martialed for speeding off the base and hiring out the cars in violation of regulations; hears about other men who have extra cars in the repair area, and who rent them out for weekends, and their serious court-martial; says that a new Captain has taken over the base, and this has caused a flurry of regulations penalties; tells a story of a “negro” soldier who tries to take a rerate exam. Listens to La Boehme on the radio.
      Subseries 7: Folders 361-370: 4 February-9 February 1945
    - Folders 361-370: 4 February-9 February 1945 (4, 7)
      Sees the movie “The Fighting Lady;” describes the lack of “terrific combat” of the Pacific theater. Wonders about why the base command shows the sailors movies that make them think about the war some days, and then comedies and such other days. Sees “Practically Yours”. Reads, for the first time, about what the Nazis are doing to the Jews in Poland. Lt. Kennedy calls Recht into his office to get a lawyer’s opinion on one of the court martial cases facing someone in their department; asks Esther to send him an apple pie. Talks about liking Bill Maudlin’s humor and cartoons. Hears about problems with the German POWs at the base. Talks about a company that has a contract selling officer uniforms being protected from losses by the Navy. Talks about the effect of the war on the lives of the people who fight in it.
      Subseries 8: Folders 371-380: 9 February 1945-14 February 1945
    - Folders 371-380: 9 February 1945-14 February 1945 (4, 8)
      Sees the movie “Experiment Perilous”. Hopes that Esther has “recovered” from his letter of last night; confesses to Esther that he has ‘spring fever’. Reads remarks by American socialists who have no love for the USSR. Hears about some sort of scandal with the female editor[Marilyn Kaemmerle] of the William and Mary News[by which he means the campus paper, The Flat Hat];[The scandal was caused by Kaemmerle publishing an editorial in the Flat Hat that supported desegregation of William and Mary. The Board of Visitors disagreed, and President Pomfret removed her from the editorship. See subject file “Flat Hat Incident of 1945” and “Marilyn Kaemmerle” for more information]; Tells Esther how mad he got at people making noise during a piano concert. Reading a book by Antoine de Saint-Exupery. Continues to write about the editor of the William and Mary News. Hears a rumor that the Camp post office is going to install an X-ray machine to stop people from sending alarm clocks, cigarettes, and other such items; asks soldiers about how they would feel working with Japanese PoWs, and they would not want to. Gets invited by Kaemmerle to come talk with her at her sorority house, Pi Beta Phi. Gets a Valentine’s day card from Esther. Hears about an incident on the camp about a German PoW scratching some swastikas onto a bus being scrapped.
      Subseries 9: Folders 381-390: 15 February 1945-25 February 1945
    - Folders 381-390: 15 February 1945-25 February 1945 (4, 9)
      Describes the office in which he works. Talks about how he usually just chats and drinks coffee while he is supposed to be working. Hears from Marilyn Kaemmerle that there have been 45 editors in the 33 year history of the Flat Hat so far. Is reading a book by Anatole France [Jacques Thibault]. Sees the movie “A Tree Grows in Brooklyn.” Debates whether or not to take a plane home after hearing of an accident. Spends a couple of hours with Marilyn Kaemmerle at her sorority house, and helps sort letters that she has been receiving; talks about the Jewish students at the school with Kaemmerle, along with the continuing reaction to her editorial. Reads a newspaper article about the treatment of German PoWs by the Russians.
      Subseries 10: Folders 391-400: 25 February 1945-8 March 1945
    - Folders 391-400: 25 February 1945-8 March 1945 (4, 10)
      Enjoys a walk in Williamsburg and a rest in the Sunken Gardens; explains the new set up of the Flat Hat; goes up to Richmond to go to a B’nai Brith dinner meeting. Talks about the difference between how enlisted men and officers are treated when they break regulations. Talks about Time and Newsweek’s depiction of the Marilyn Kaemmerle incident; has another meeting with her and some of her sorority sisters. Recommends “The Little Prince” to Esther. Talks about his preparations for his upcoming leave. Gets new men into the repairs and transportation departments, who have never worked on a gas engine, only diesel ones. Returns to the camp from leave; gets a small crate of his accumulated mail from his leave; gets his marks from the rerate test.
  Series 5: Folders 401-500: 9 March 1945-3 June 1945
- Folders 401-500: 9 March 1945-3 June 1945
  - (5)
      Subseries 1: Folders 401-410: 9 March 1945-13 March 1945
    - Folders 401-410: 9 March 1945-13 March 1945 (5, 1)
      Talks with one of the truck dispatchers about freight transportation; hears reports about the bombing of Cologne. Lists all of the periodicals that he reads; fears the worst for what Germans to do Jewish Allied POWs; while cleaning out the office files he finds some long expired credit cards that Lt. Kennedy just happened to need that day. Discusses how, even though he was a lawyer in civilian life, he would not care to be a military lawyer; does not like the editorializing comments under some of the captions of Japanese prisoners. Laments the fact that he can never read all that he wishes to. Discusses the quality of education in the US with Lt. Sorensen; reads an article that there are too many men in the service doing too little; meets a Jewish girl on the bus; sees two soldiers fight for a chance to give a woman their seat. Sees a short about Iwo Jima, and how horrible it was there. Hears the end of some discussion on the “Negro problem,” and joins in the discussion.
      Subseries 2: Folders 411-420: 14 March 1945-21 March 1945
    - Folders 411-420: 14 March 1945-21 March 1945 (5, 2)
      Some of the POWs who work in the mess hall go “on strike” and are replaced; calls Marilyn Kaemmerle and gets an update on her situation. Sees pictures of the bombing of Dresden; Lt. Kennedy does not mind talking about social problems, but does not see much of a point in them. Sees the movie “The Unseen;” hears about the return of some German POWs who had escaped; hears about a policy that says the Army will take draftees age 18-21, and the Navy will take draftees 21-38; reads a letter in the newspaper from a Navy sailor who is a William and Mary graduate, who disagrees with the Board of Visitors on the Marilyn Kaemmerle issue. Talks about how the “loafing” of the men who have just come from the sea is not good for the morale of the camp regulars. Goes on leave to see Esther in Washington, DC. On the return trip from Washington, talks with a sailor about the National Gallery. Hears that one of his friends is in legal trouble for selling meat over the price ceiling; is told about race and segregation trouble at the theater. Hears from a person at that theater that there had been no problem at all, just rumors; rides with a young African-American soldier on the bus, and hears about his training.
      Subseries 3: Folders 421-430: 21 March 1945-25 March 1945
    - Folders 421-430: 21 March 1945-25 March 1945 (5, 3)
      Hears about a friend who was transferred from his department for requesting additional leave after his father died; Tries to get a friend who is going back to Pittsburgh to bring back an apple pie from Esther; is angry that there are conditions that make war necessary; has a friend who sees a newsreel of murdered Poles and Jews, and cannot believe that humans could be “guilty of such deeds.” Hears his friends on how the Japanese could be more expected to murder than the Germans, because they are “heathens.” Is reading the book “Citizen Tom Paine” that takes liberties with history; theorizes that some servicemen are beginning to consider war their profession. Hears that he has the reputation of being the most avid book reader; hears about another incident involving race on the camp; reads about how the meat famine may just be a creation of the meat packers, not an actual shortage. Talks with a POW about the situation in Germany. The Captain makes a separate bus stop for the African-American soldiers, but he makes it close to their separate USO, as they used to have a long walk to get there; mails out more chocolate and cigarettes to people back home; is trying to find information about the African-American actor Ira Alldridge; talks about another racial incident[in a seemingly unconnected letter fragment]. Is curious in hearing about the situation of the Jews in Italy, as compared to Germany. Draws a map of the garden and the area around the hut he lives in; while playing some classical music, one of the POWs sticks his head in the hut to compliment the music, and Recht notices all the POWs sitting around outside are listening to his music; reads a book studying the lives of Orthodox Jews. Spends a day in Williamsburg and eats at the Lodge, as he often does; hopes that the war will be over a little sooner than expected.
      Subseries 4: Folders 431-440: 26 March 1945-31 March 1945
    - Folders 431-440: 26 March 1945-31 March 1945 (5, 4)
      Reads a book that talks about Black Mountain College. Hears rumors of the “imminent possibility of Nazi surrender”; tells Esther about how much money he will get when he gets out of service. Talks with another soldier about going to Richmond for a Seder meal. Is confused by a friend ending a letter to him with “Love to Esther. Anything you want?”; the men living in the hut each contribute a little bit of money to buy flowers for their garden. Describes to Esther the Passover Seder that he attended. Comments that the services at camp offer nothing stimulating, so he will not go on a regular basis. Talks with a man at the Temple in Richmond who owns a clothes plant that makes many of the uniforms for soldiers, along with suits for civilians. Talks about how the Rabbi at Passover had to quiet down the participants during the service; is polite and civil to the German POWs, but not trusting; hears rumors of the Allied armies making inroads into Germany.
      Subseries 5: Folders 441-450: 31 March 1945-4 April 1945
    - Folders 441-450: 31 March 1945-4 April 1945 (5)
      Hears a lot of contradictory information regarding China, its Communists, and the KMT; notices how businesses complain about the lack of business when they are actually doing better than ever. Fragment that talks about Walter White’s book. Hears about a dance contest for enlisted men, but cannot get down there in time; reads about a French pastor who quotes Pasteur over his door. Compares what he hears about the treatment of Allied POWs to what he sees the treatment is of the German POWs. Gives a description of the town of Gottingen from a book he is reading; has a friend who believes that the Russians will attack Japan as soon as Germany is defeated. Begins to get a cold wave after the beginning of an early summer. Tells Esther to tell one of the people he knows, Lt. Boreman, that he is to be a legal officer for the camp. Sees the movie “Hotel Berlin”; hears that the POWs are allowed a German newspaper from New York City; hears about Nazi leaders escaping through Spain to Argentina. Reads a book that is a “report on the Negro’s status in World War II,” that has an introduction from Eleanor Roosevelt.
      Subseries 6: Folders 451-460: 5 April 1945-10 April 1945
    - Folders 451-460: 5 April 1945-10 April 1945 (5, 6)
      Reads that Russia will not renew its treaty with Japan and that Japan’s cabinet has fallen. Makes a visit to Richmond, but returns early; reads a story in the paper about German slave workers brought to Germany from conquered countries. Hears that the Nazi’s have one of Stalin’s sons as a hostage. Has to do laundry because of an inspection the next day; talks with a few sailors who are up before the Captain the next day for speeding off the base, and being away without leave. Two members of the office skip the inspection because they were supposedly out until three a.m. driving people back to Richmond and Hampton, but they in fact never made their second trip and merely slept in. Hears a story of how every sailor who goes out to sea is given a hammock, but they are only used for covering the bed and sheets to prevent them from getting dirty. Reads a story about a Rabbi who traveled through all of the war zones and did not hear of any racial or religious prejudice. Sends Esther an article about segregation in the camp theater. Talks about how, even with all his talking, it is hard to change the prejudices of people. Has another discussion with the men in the office about the segregation of the theater.
      Subseries 7: Folders 461-470: 11 April 1945-17 April 1945
    - Folders 461-470: 11 April 1945-17 April 1945 (5, 7)
      Is told that it is not proper for offices and enlisted men to socialize outside of the workplace or in public; hears that Lt. Kennedy used to be a pro football ref before the war. Recht’s friend from home, Len, is installed as a camp lawyer; goes to a concert at the College. Hears the news of the death of FDR, and hopes that Truman reveals himself to be more than he fears him to be; feels that the graciousness of FDR will be sorely missed in the negotiations after the war; Kennedy tells a member of the legal department at Peary that Recht was a lawyer, and the lawyer seems interested in stealing Recht for his own department. Hears that all the men with 2 years of service by Sept 30, 1945 will be shipped out to sea soon. Gets a “new colored fellow” into the office, the first one for Recht’s department. Recht decides he does not feel like taking on the busywork of the attorney’s office, would rather stick with his own. Esther may not be able to come down to the Camp because her mother is ill. Suggests ways to use the welfare fund money of the camp, such as a tennis court or records. Confronts a member of the office about not dressing the way the others do, and lying to Lt. Kennedy to get this.
      Subseries 8: Folders 471-480: 17 April 1945-22 May 1945
    - Folders 471-480: 17 April 1945-22 May 1945 (5, 8)
      Watches a news broadcast of Roosevelt’s funeral. Thinks about telling his fellow sailors about the similarity between racial prejudice and Nazi ideology, but then sees a magazine that already did it. Enjoys Esther’s visit, even if it was short. Has so much work he cannot even get off a letter like normal. Reads about a person from Pittsburgh who is charged a fine of $12,000 for overcharging customers. Wouldn’t be at all surprised at an Allied landing on the China coast. One of the other people in his department gets a house that the USO found for him and for his wife to stay.
      Subseries 9: Folders 481-490: 22 May 1945-28 May 1945
    - Folders 481-490: 22 May 1945-28 May 1945 (5, 9)
      Has to go to the mess to see what all the boys were complaining about, and finds the food there to be just fine; Lt. Kennedy’s wife borrows a magazine from Recht that is entirely edited by African-Americans. Cannot get interested enough to try and get a higher rate, up to a Y2c. One of his office mates is itching to get his transfer out, and gets out half a day early because Recht covers for him. Hears that the College is going to put on a swing concert, and thinks about going to that; visits with his friend who is now a lawyer at the Camp, with whom Recht went to law school; Lt. Kennedy sees the first African American officer on the base. Most of the restaurants in Williamsburg are declared off limits for servicemen because of the unsanitary condition of the kitchens. One of Recht’s friends from home is assigned to the Pacific theater; talks about Esther’s father’s business; Recht critiques the OPA price minimums. Gets another African-American into their department, as a driver; gives his impressions of the members of Truman’s cabinet that he has read of. Recht cannot totally dedicate himself to dieting, as he likes the mashed potatoes too much. A man who’s been in the Navy 18 months who gets transferred into Recht’s department has been taught to read and write by the Navy since he was drafted; Lt. Kennedy is forced to transfer some men, and picks the ones who went to a show while on duty.
      Subseries 10: Folders 491-500: 29 May 1945-3 June 1945
    - Folders 491-500: 29 May 1945-3 June 1945 (5, 10)
      Tells the story of one of the men who was forced to transfer by Lt. Kennedy. Goes to a chorus production that he somewhat enjoys, with mostly African-American singers and songs. Hears about an African-American author who has written a book about Reconstruction. Mentions that one of his friends, whose father just died, had been a doctor in the court of the Czar. Hears that people who have two years service as of December 31, 1945 will be the next group discharged. Is going to listen on the radio to a program about staying friends with the USSR after the end of the War; hears, from Esther, that the government is cracking down on meat restrictions. Is planning to have Esther down in Williamsburg for four weeks, starting early August and ending after Rosh Hashanah; describes the work that he did that day. Sees the movie “Objective Burma;” seems to be missing on of his jumpers. Calls Marilyn Kaemmerle again, to check up on her; wants to a say personal goodbye to her before she graduates; the commissary begins rationing meat to 4 oz. per person per day. Goes reading at the Williamsburg pool, with a lot of College girls there; sees a lot of parents in town for graduation, with only 125 in the class. Gets a call late at night from another person in his department, asking Recht to cover for him since he is in Richmond; on the phone, Recht can hear much mumbling of female voices.
  Series 6: Folders 501-600: 4 June 1945 to 5 September 1945
- Folders 501-600: 4 June 1945 to 5 September 1945
  - (6)
      Subseries 1: Folders 501-510: 4 June 1945-8 June 1945
    - Folders 501-510: 4 June 1945-8 June 1945 (6, 1)
      Goes to the graduation exercises at the College of William and Mary; gets to say good-bye to Marilyn Kaemmerle. Is worried that the hard work in Europe is now upon them, since the war itself is over; hears that the Navy discharge age is lowered to 38. Wonders about the marriage of his friend, Blanche, who is living “a rather complex life these days.” Recht’s friend Lew has to go to Portsmouth to get glasses, provided by the Navy; sees the movie “Conflict.” People in his office try to get a frying pan to have eggs in the office; comments about recent articles in a magazine that he subscribes to, dealing with the state of post-war Europe. Discusses a court-martial that a sailor is under for killing a woman in a car crash. Has to buy another white jumper because the laundry messed his up, discusses prices of military clothes. Talks about the array of maps he has on his desk, including one of where American pilots can hit Japan, maps from newspapers, etc. Is able to iron for the first time in some months; describes his fascination with the smell of coffee, even over the drink itself; sees the movie “Those Endearing Young Charms;” reads a Bureau of Naval Personnel memo that describes, humorously, the kind of life that Recht leads.
      Subseries 2: Folders 511-520: 9 June 1945-15 June 1945
    - Folders 511-520: 9 June 1945-15 June 1945 (6, 2)
      Reads about the Virginia State Supreme Court upholding a segregation law, as well as a Federal Circuit Court of Appeals case on the same matter; reads reports about what Congress is going to do about conscription after the war ends. Spends an afternoon in Williamsburg, sitting out near the pool and eating toast and jelly, something he never has in camp. Hears a story about Kirsten Flagstad, who may or may not have sung for the Nazis in Berlin; reads a comparison of amount of food available for servicemen each year, 220 lbs, as opposed to civilians, 70lbs. Gives Esther plans for his leave, hopefully a week earlier than expected. Talks about mailing Jello to their friend Ruthie. Tells a story about how he heard a noise late at night, and thought it could be prisoners escaping or some sort of thing, but it turns out to be just a short. Talks about the pet squirrel that they have captured, for which the German prisoners built a cage.
      Subseries 3: Folders 521-530: 14 June 1945-26 June 1945
    - Folders 521-530: 14 June 1945-26 June 1945 (6, 3)
      Enjoys a trip home to see Esther, for about a week. Has to get to the barber shop to get his hair cut before inspection. Describes his trip back to the base, on a B&O train, sitting next to a girl who seems prudish, but talks to her about her life as a Cornell student. Gives a description of what inspection entails. Lt. Kennedy is getting angry at a sailor for not caring enough, just floating along and waiting to get transferred; hears the newest rules about rerates, saying that everyone must take a general exam as well as a specialist exam; mentions a story from the Pearyscope about a man who was in the Army, discharged, and enlisted in the Navy, and the hardships he has had. Hears a rumor that Peary is to become the only boot training station east of the Mississippi; notices that a Negro office had been transferred. Gets free glasses from the Navy; wants to go see programs in PBK Hall related to the Literature, Folk Music, Politics, etc., of Latin America. Finds out that he is going to be switching jobs with a man whose work Lt. Kennedy does not like. Sees the movie “Thrill of Romance.”
      Subseries 4: Folders 531- 540: 26 June 1945-1 July 1945
    - Folders 531- 540: 26 June 1945-1 July 1945 (6, 4)